"Wombat, let's go on a
treasure hunt in the forest",
said Piyokichi.
"Piyokichi, I'm feeling kind
of drowsy so maybe another
time",
replied Wombat,
and he soon fell back to sleep.
≪（ドアの開く音）
（公生）ん？
（紘子）お願い！
（早希）もう　しょうがないわね。
Please!
Really... What am I going to do with you?
（紘子）♪♪「旦那のアホ」→
Idiot husband!
（公生）紘ちゃん
また　旦那さんと　ケンカしたの？
Spend more time on me!
Or I'm gonna step out on you!
（紘子）ケンカじゃないわ。
これは　戦争よ。→
謝ったら　金輪際　おしまいなの。
Hiro, did you have another fight with your husband?
ふ～ん。
This is no fight. This is war!
Over my dead body will I apologize to him!
公生…。
あんた　何で　ピアノ　弾けてるの？
Idiot husband!
Spend more time on me!
ん？　どうして　弾けないの？
Or I'm gonna step out on you!
Kousei...
You...
How can you play the piano?
（紘子）早希！
公生をピアニストにしよう！→
Why wouldn't I be able to play the piano?
公生は…　公生は…→
天才だよ！
Saki!
Let's turn Kousei into a pianist!
Kousei's...
a genius!
I'm heading out now.
（公生）僕　行きます。
By yourself?
（紘子）一人で？
（公生）はい。
Yes.
Are you serious?
（紘子）本気？
（公生）はい。
Yes.
What are you going to play? Without a violi—
（紘子）何を弾くつもり？
バイオリンなしじゃ…。
（公生）曲目は　変えません。
I'm not changing the piece.
（三池）
《あんなの　音楽でも何でもない》
It's not even music!
（公生）僕　悔しいんです。
See, I'm pissed.
（公生）だから　証明します。
So I'm going to prove it.
宮園かをりが
どれほどの演奏家か。
Just how great a musician Miyazono Kaori is.
それに　じゃじゃ馬の
至上命令なんです。
And besides...
this is a supreme directive from that wayward girl.
ガラコンは
目立って　なんぼですから。
These galas are all about standing out.
（観客）これって
バイオリンのコンサートだろ？
Wait, isn't this is a violin concert?
（観客）
伴奏者が　一人だけで　弾くの？
Is that accompanist going to play on his own?
《全部　君のせいだ。
君が僕を　舞台に戻したから》
This is all your fault.
Because you put me back on the stage.
《いつも　君が僕を突き動かす》
You always move me.
（武士）《俺を見ろ！》
（絵見）《私を見ろ！》
Look at me!
（かをり）《私を見ろ！》
《僕を見ろ！》
Look at me!
《証明してやる。　僕は　すごい》
I'm going to prove it.
That I'm incredible.
That Miyazono Kaori, who's named me to be her accompanist...
《僕を伴奏者に据える
宮園かおりは…》
《もっと　すごい！》
is even more incredible!
Once again, unprecedented! Arima again?
（風間）《再び　前代未聞。
また　有馬か！》
（審査員）
《伴奏じゃない。　これは…》
This isn't the accompaniment. This is...
（絵見）《クライスラー　『愛の悲しみ』
ラフマニノフ　ピアノ編曲版》
Kreisler's "Love's Sorrow"...
Rachmaninoff's piano arrangement.
[ﾃﾚﾋﾞ]♪♪（『愛の悲しみ』の演奏）
（紘子）《早希が　好きだった曲》→
The piece that Saki loved...
《一人で　ずっと
向き合ってたのね》→
So you've been facing it alone all this time.
《でも　あんたの知ってる
『愛の悲しみ』は→
But...
was the "Love's Sorrow" that you've always known really like this?
そんな曲だった？》
《見てろ　見てろ　見てろ！》
Just watch...
Just watch... Just watch...
《僕は　すごい！
宮園かをりは…》
I'm incredible.
Miyazono Kaori is...
《もっと　すごい！》
even more incredible!
GALA CONCERT
（観客）《すげえ》
（観客）《大迫力》
Unbelievable!
So powerful!
（落合）《がっかりね》→
What a disappointment.
《ただ　怒りを
ぶつけてるだけ》→
He's only venting his anger.
《粗雑さと　たけだけしさを
はき違えてる》→
He's confusing crudeness with ferocity.
This grates on my ears.
《耳障りだわ》
《あれ？
僕　こんなに強く　たたいてた？》
Huh?
Was I pounding the keys that hard?
My whole body is taut.
《体中に　力が入ってる》
《こんなんじゃ　駄目だ》
This won't do at all.
《この曲は
こんな弾き方じゃないよな》
This piece isn't supposed to be played like this.
《いつも聴いていた　この曲は
僕の子守歌だった》
The piece that I always listened to was...
It was my lullaby...
《この曲は…》
《おかしいな》
I don't understand.
As usual, I can't hear the notes.
《いつもみたいに
音が　聞こえないのに→
僕の中に　音がある》
But I can feel the sound inside me.
《それは　音に束縛されない
ってことじゃないかな》→
It might mean you're not bound by auditory perception.
《願いや　思いを込めた音を
感じる瞬間は　なかった？》
Wasn't there ever a moment when you sensed
the notes permeating with your desires and emotions?
（紘子）《音が　聞こえなくなる。
きっと　それは　贈り物だよ》
Losing your ability to hear yourself play is nothing short of a gift.
（早希）《公生。　もっと優しく》→
Kousei...
Play it more gently.
Like you're caressing a baby's head.
《赤ちゃんの頭を　なでるように》
（早希）
《抱き締めるように　弾くのよ》
Play it like you're embracing him.
《母さん》
Mom...
《この曲　母さんなら
こう弾いたかな》
This piece... If it were her,
would she have played it like this?
（落合）《演奏が　変わった》
His playing style just changed...
He's doing it again.
（絵見）《まただ。　音が変わる》
The sound is changing.
（椿）《公生…》
Kousei...
（紘子）《早希だ。　早希がいる》
It's Saki.
Saki is there...
（紘子）早希！
いくら何でも　やり過ぎよ！→
Saki!
Even for you, that's going too far!
血が出るほど
殴りつけるなんて→
Hitting him hard enough to draw blood is crossing the line!
ひど過ぎるわ。
それでも　母親？→
How can you call yourself a mother?
公生は　あんたに
喜んでほしくて　頑張ってたのよ。
Kousei was doing his best just to make you happy!
Of course I know that!
分かってるわよ　そんなこと！
Saki!
（紘子）早希！
（早希）分かってるわ。　でも→
I do know that...
But...
私には　時間がないの。
I'm... running out of time.
早希…。
Saki...
Towa High School
Music Festival
助けて　助けてよ。
Help me...
Towa High School
Music Festival
Please help me...
Towa High School
Music Festival
誰か　助けて。
Somebody help me...
The notes...
音が…　ピアノが…
僕の耳が…。
The piano...
My ears...
音が　聞こえないよ。
They can't hear the notes!
誰か　助けてよ。
Somebody, please help me...
お母さん…。
Mom...
（紘子）《公生。
あんたを追い詰めたのは　私だ》→
Kousei...
I'm the one who drove you into this corner.
《私が　あんたを
ピアニストにしようなんて言ったから》
It's all because I told her to turn you into a pianist.
（紘子）ごめんね。
I'm so sorry...
（紘子）《音楽が　公生を
苦しめるものでしかないのに》
If music only brings Kousei pain and suffering...
（紘子）ごめんね。
I'm so sorry...
Then I shouldn't be allowed to stay by his side.
（紘子）《私は　この子のそばに
いては　いけないんだ》
I'm sorry...
（紘子）ごめんね。　ごめんね。
（紘子）《でも…》
But...
（紘子）《公生は　戻ってきた》
Kousei returned.
What made you come back to the piano?
（紘子）何が　あんたを
ピアノに向かわせたの？
I want to see that sight again with my own eyes one more time.
僕は　もう一度
その光景を体験したい。
思ったんです。
That's what made me think...
変な　ピアニストに
なりたいなって。
I'd like to become a really weird pianist!
After losing Saki, Kousei...
（紘子）《早希を失った　公生は→
met someone who means the world to him.
掛け替えのない　誰かと
出会ったのね》→
《公生が　信じてるのに
ピアニストの私が→
If Kousei believes in that,
then as a pianist, how can I not believe in the power of music?
音楽の力を信じないわけには
いかないじゃない》
（紘子）
《早希。　ちゃんと見ててよ》→
Saki, be sure to watch this.
《私たちの息子が
最後のお別れをしに行くから》
Our dear boy
is about to bid you a last farewell.
《ああ…　やっぱり
思わずには　いられない》
Oh...
I can't help thinking about her, after all.
《この曲は
母さんの　においがする》
This piece reminds me of my mom.
（かをり）
《君は　誰のために弾くの？》
Who do you want to play it for?
《届くかな？　届くといいな》
Will it reach her?
I can only hope so.
（早希）私が　いなくなったら
公生は　どうなるの？→
After I'm gone,
what's going to become of Kousei?
Will he be able to earn a living?
ちゃんと　生活できる？
Can he make music his livelihood?
音楽で　食べていける？
今　私に　できることは→
All I can do right now is make him
play accurately, faithful to the score.
譜面を忠実に
正確に　弾かせること。→
手に技術さえ　あれば→
As long as he has the skills, he just might be able to support himself someday.
将来　何とか
食べていけるかもしれない。
What a terrible mother I am...
（早希）ひどい　母親。→
There's nothing I can leave that boy...
あの子に
何も　残してあげられない。→
毎朝　歯磨き　できるかしら。→
Will he brush his teeth every morning?
どこでも　寝ちゃうから
風邪　ひかないかしら。→
He falls asleep anywhere,
so what if he catches a cold?
運動が　苦手だから
大ケガ　しないかしら。→
He isn't good at sports,
so what if he gets seriously injured?
もっと
そばにいてあげたかった。→
I wish I could've stayed with him longer...
Will my treasure...
私の宝物は　幸せになれるかしら。
find happiness?
《知ってたんだ》
I knew all along.
《母さんの亡霊は
僕が　つくり出した　影》
The ghost of my mom was a shadow of my own creation.
《逃げ出すための　理由》
An excuse for me to run away.
《僕の弱さ》
My own weakness.
《母さんは
もう　あの場所にいない》
Mom isn't there anymore.
《母さんは　僕の中に　いる》
Mom is...
inside me.
《そうだよね》
Yes, that's right.
《ピアノは
抱き締めるように　弾くんだよね》
The piano...
is meant to be played like you're embracing it, right?
ねえねえ　お母さん。
Hey, Mom?
『愛の喜び』と
『愛の悲しみ』があるのに→
There's both "Love's Joy" and "Love's Sorrow", so why do you always play "Love's Sorrow"?
どうして　いつも
『愛の悲しみ』を弾くの？
それはね…。
I play it so...
（早希）
悲しみに　慣れておくためよ。
you'll get used to sorrow.
（紘子）
《私たちは　つながっている》→
We're all connected.
Just like the notes are intermittently connected,
《音が　断続的に　つながるように
私たちは　共有している》→
it's shared by us all.
Through music...
《音楽を通して
知っている　誰かと→
With the people you know,
知らない　誰かと
世界中の誰かと》
with the people you don't know,
with all the people in the world.
（かをり）《君も　行こう》
You come too!
《誰かと　同じように
母さんとも　つながっている》
Just like with her, I'm connected to Mom too.
《そう信じているから
僕は　進むんだ》
I'm moving forward because I believe that.
《だから…　だから…》
So...
Goodbye...
《さよなら》
Your Lie in April
Goodbye...
≪（物音）
（三池）あっ。
ハハッ。　膝が　笑ってる。
My knees are shaking...
気が　抜けたかな。
Guess I'm exhausted?
（三池）あっ。
≪（紘子）公生！　公生！
Kousei!
（小春）うぁ～！
どわ～！
≪（紘子）フッ。
モテモテだね　色男。
Hey, look at you, hot stuff!
娘が　男の胸に
飛び込んだなんて　知ったら→
If my husband hears that his daughter threw
herself into a man's arms, he'll be devastated.
旦那　泣くわね。
ハハ…。
So did you get to see Saki?
早希には　会えた？
母さんは　いつも　近くにいました。
My mom...
She's always been by my side.
Yes.
ピアノのタッチも　指の運びも
ペダルを　キュッと踏む癖も→
The way I touch the keys, the way I move my fingers, my habit of squeezing the pedals,
my tastes, the order that I eat...
味の好みも　食べる順番も→
My mom is in every little gesture of mine.
僕の　ちょっとした　しぐさに
母さんがいる。
僕らは…　僕と母さんは
つながっている。
We're...
Mom and I are...
connected.
紘子さん。
母さんに　届いたかな。
Hiroko, do you think it reached my mom?
僕の　精いっぱいのピアノ。
The way I played my very best...
母さんに　届いたかな。
Do you think it reached my mom?
You dummy.
（紘子）バカ。　あんたたちは
つながってるんでしょ。
You two are connected, aren't you?
届いたに　決まってんじゃん。
Of course it reached her!
《音楽があったから
出会えた　瞬間がある》
Because of music,
I was given the chance to meet others.
I was moved by those encounters.
《出会えた　感動がある》
《出会えた　人たちがいる》
There are people that I got to meet.
《出会えた　思いがある》
There were emotions I got to discover.
《これは　全部→
These are all...
ピアノを　僕に教えてくれた
母さんが残してくれた　思い出》
memories that my mom, who taught me how to play the piano, left me.
《母さん　僕は　幸せだよ》
Mom, I'm happy.
Thank you.
《ありがとう　ありがとう》
《さよなら》
Goodbye.
（観客）すてきだったなぁ。
That was so exquisite.
I'm ready to just go home now!
（観客）もう　帰っても
いいくらいだ。
（観客）次の演奏か。
Oh, the next performance, huh?
（観客）今　音　いらねぇ。
I don't want to hear anything right now.
（三池）《舞台に立つのが
こんなに怖いなんて》
I never thought I'd be so scared to go onstage.
（風間）《三池君…》
Miike...
（審査員）《これは　つらいな》
Now this is a tough act to follow...
（三池）《逃げ出したい。　あっ》
I want to run away...
（三池）《ママ…》
Mother...
（三池）《僕は　あそこまで
精いっぱい　やっただろうか》→
Have I ever played my heart out like he did?
《あそこまで
真摯に　向き合っただろうか》→
Have I ever played with as much sincerity as he did?
《僕も　あそこまで
身も心も　捧げてみたい》→
I want to see if I can sacrifice body and soul like that.
《燃焼してみたい》→
I want to see if I can give it my all.
《見てて！》
Just watch me.
Right now, all I want to do is hear my mother's voice.
（三池）《今は　無性に
ママの声が　聞きたいよ》
（観客）あれ？
（風間）《ん？》
Huh?
Is his playing softer than usual?
（審査員）《いつもより
音が　柔らかい？》→
I see...
《そうか。
君も　打ち抜かれたか》→
So your heart's been pierced too?
《君たちも　高め合うのか》
And you're both going to raise the bar, eh?
（絵見）あ～　面白かった。
（落合）バイオリンは　いいわね。
That was awesome.
Isn't violin music lovely?
（絵見）先生。
（落合）うん？
Ms. Ochiai?
I'm glad that I'm a musician.
（絵見）私　音楽やってて　よかった。
（落合）ウフッ。
ha
To obliterate a powerful enemy.
Now that's the ultimate pleasure!
ha
強敵を　ぶちのめす！
これぞ　至上の悦楽。
ha
A bona fide extreme sadist?
（落合）《真性ドＳ》
ha
（渡）おっ　公生。　…と　お姉さま。
Kousei...
and his older friend!
おーい！
（椿）公生！
Hey!
Kousei...
（椿）
《あれ？　あれ？　おかしいな》→
Huh?
This is so weird.
《言葉が　出てこないや。　変なの》
I can't find the words to say.
Freaky...
（渡）もう　帰っちまって
いいのか？
Is it okay for you to just leave?
いいんじゃない？
僕なんか　おまけの　おまけだし。
Well, why not? I was just a throw-in for the throw-in.
それに…。
And besides...
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
I've got to find that throw-in who
blew me off, and rip her a new one.
トンズラかました　おまけに
おきゅうを据えないとね。
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
He's mad.
R
a
g
e
（椿）《怒ってる》
（渡）《怒ってる？》
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
Is he mad?
R
a
g
e
R
a
g
e
じゃあ　帰ろっか。
色々　疲れたよ。
All right, ready to head home? I'm exhausted from all this.
（小春）ジュース　飲みたい。
I want some juice!
Your mom could go for some too.
（紘子）あ～　お母ちゃんも
飲みたいわ。
Tsubaki,
椿。　頑張った僕に　一言　ないの？
you've got nothing to say to me after all my hard work?
えっ？　えっと…。
Huh?
Um...
何か　大人っぽい。
You look all grown up.
何だよ　それ。
褒めてほしかったのに。
What's up with that?
I was hoping you'd praise me.
《あれ？　あれれ？　変なの》→
Huh?
What the heck?
So weird...
If I don't hold them in, I might shed tears.
《こらえてないと
涙が出そう…　涙？》→
Tears?
Is it because I'm able to talk to Kousei like I always do that I'm tearing up with relief?
《公生と　いつもどおり話せて
ほっとした　涙？》→
残念な涙？》
Or is it because I'm only able to talk to him like I always do
that I'm tearing up with disappointment?
Gala Concert
（紘子）見に来てたなら→
If you were there at the concert,
you could've said something to me.
一言　おっしゃってくだされば
いいのに。
You're as spiteful as ever, aren't you,
相変わらず　お人が悪いですね。→
落合先生。
（落合）フッ。
Ms. Ochiai?
I wouldn't have expected that Arima was being mentored by you.
有馬君が
あなたに　師事していたなんて→
意外だったわ。
After all, ever since Arima Saki passed away, you never went near that house.
有馬　早希が　他界してから
あの家には　近づかなかったのに。→
あの子も　変わったわ。
面白い　演奏家になった。
That boy has changed too.
He's become quite an intriguing musician.
Yes.
はい。
Instilling something into his music,
音に　何かを宿し
聴いた人間に　何かを残す。→
leaving something in those who hear it.
あいつは　表現者としての道を
再び　歩みだしました。→
That kid has taken his first steps forward as an artist.
でも　有馬　早希を失ったことは→
But...
the loss of Arima Saki
公生にとって　私にとって
残念なことですが→
was tragic for Kousei, and for me.
But I wonder if he, as a musician, really had to face through it all.
有馬　公生という
演奏家にとって→
必要なことだったんでしょうか。
（落合）《有馬君の演奏には
どこか悲しみが　つきまとう》→
There's an ever-present sorrow hanging over Arima's music.
《最愛の母の死が　彼に何かを
もたらしたのだとしたら→
If the death of his beloved mother triggered something in him,
TOTSUHARA UNIVERSITY HOSPITAL
それは　鬼の通る道だ》
then it's a grim path that he must walk.
Miyazono Kaori
（紘子）《悲しみが　成長させる。
公生が　進むのなら…》
For his growth to be spurred by sorrow...
If Kousei is to walk that path,
Episode 13
Love's Sorrow
（紘子）
《失って　進むのかもしれない》
he might have to lose someone to keep walking.
Episode 14
Footprints
No two dreams can be the same
sore zore no yume wo erande
Episode 14
Footprints
No two dreams can be the same
sore zore no yume wo erande
Watch next week too!